Special Committee on the Structure of the University Records, 1967-1970 (bulk 1968-1969): Finding Aid AC044
University Archives
Special Committee on the Structure of the University Records
1967-1970
1968-1969
University Archives
Princeton University. Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections
Princeton University. Special Committee on the Structure of the University
AC044
14 boxes
2 items
The 1960s was a tumultuous decade in the history of the United States. Prominent on a landscape of political assassinations, civil rights, and the fight for gender equality was the prolonged conflict in Vietnam. Although discontent was growing against the war in Southeast Asia, the largest and most vocal expression against America's involvement was compellingly articulated on college campuses throughout the nation. Author Thomas Powers notes that the war in Vietnam was, for America, "one of those things that come along once in a generation and call entire societies into question, forcing people to choose between irreconcilables." One of those irreconcilables, for the Princeton community of students and faculty, was their exclusion from university decisions that involved everything from university parietals to Princeton's association with the Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA). In response to student demonstrations and faculty protests, Princeton President Robert F. Goheen established the Committee on the Structure of the University to examine Princeton University's governance and explore how it could be more inclusive of the university community in making decisions. The Kelley Committee, as it came to be known, would be responsible for the introduction of perhaps the most sweeping administrative changes in the University's history and establishing the Council of the Princeton University Community (CPUC).
Scope and Contents
Consists primarily of correspondence, memoranda, and reports generated by Stanley Kelley, Chair of the Special Committee on the Structure of the University, also known as the Kelley Committee. Background material on student organization, the Institute for Defense Analysis, and numerous facets of college governance rounds out the collection.
Arrangement
The collections is divided into six series and arranged alphabetically by topic as follows:
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the archives on March 22, 1996. by Stanley Kelley (AR1996-24).
Appraisal
No appraisal information is available.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital images of series 1-5, created in 2009, are accessible in the contents list.
Biographical / Historical
The Vietnam War was fought by the United States from 1965 to 1973 and represented a turbulent period in America's history. It was the longest war in which the United States had been engaged, and nightly television coverage of the horrors of war caused many Americans to question the relevance of U.S. presence in a conflict that was taking place halfway around the world. The conflict gave rise to the largest and most successful anti-war movement in United States history. The college campus was the locus of many demonstrations held to decry the perceived immorality of the war, and Princeton was not immune. The 1967-1968 academic year was a tense one for the Princeton community. A number of issues were being hotly debated on campus: the future of the Army Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC) program and military recruitment, counseling students about the draft, the rule regarding women visitors in dormitories, and the relationship of the University to the Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA). On May 2, 1968, demonstrators marched on campus with the rallying cry "Community Control of Community Affairs" and demanded that the administration change their policies on all of these issues. The largest demonstration in Princeton's history, more than 1,100 participants marched on Nassau Hall to protest the exclusion of students and faculty from university decision-making. Peter Kaminsky, president of the Undergraduate Assembly (UGA), criticized University Trustees and Administration for what he called an "arrogant dismissal of student and faculty demands." The University, in the view of demonstrators, should be "a community of students and faculty, not businessmen." Their primary demand was a complete break with the IDA. The IDA, a Washington-based nonprofit research organization whose principal customer was the Department of Defense, was under the direction of retired General Maxwell D. Taylor, who also served as a special presidential assistant to Vietnam. Concerned members of the Princeton Community expressed that association with IDA suggested a corporate stand on political issues, something that the University had traditionally avoided. "Change and advance in the university," observed University President Robert F. Goheen, "must always be pursued by argument and debate, by reasoning rather than force." In May 1968, Goheen established the Committee on the Structure of the University to be the agent of change for Princeton University. For its representatives on what would come to be known as The Kelley Committee, the faculty appointed David P. Billington, professor of civil engineering; F. Sheldon Hackney, assistant professor of history; Suzanne Keller, professor of sociology; Stanley Kelley Jr., professor of politics; Harold W. Kuhn, professor of mathematical economics; Aaron Lemonick, professor of physics; John H. Marks, associate professor of Near Eastern studies; and R. Bruce Partridge II, assistant professor of physics. President Goheen was a member ex officio. The Undergraduate Assembly (UGA) chose Richard D, Darby Jr. '69, W. Joseph Dehner Jr. '70, UGA President Peter J. Kaminsky '69, and UGA Vice President Thomas G. Travis '69. An open meeting of graduate students selected Robert A. Nerenberg '69, William H. Tucker '72, and Dan. W. Verser '74. In June 1968, Kelley, who had been chosen to chair the new 16-member group, along with several other committee members stayed in Princeton to conduct research on university governance, particularly that of Princeton. On September 30, 1968, Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) voted that the three student members of the structure committee who belonged to SDS (Kaminsky, Tucker, and Nerenberg) should leave the committee because, they charged, it fostered an illusion of reform while actually rejecting any serious university restructure. At an open meeting of the committee on October 8, 1968, SDS's Radical Arts Troope interrupted the hearings with a three-act mini-play, and 28 minutes into the session the three dissenting members left the committee; 40 other supporters in SDS joined them. The committee issued an interim report on November 21, 1968 recommending the formation of a university-wide senate and more delegation of power by the trustees in certain areas, particularly with regard to dormitory parietals. In May 1969, the Trustees' Executive Committee had set up their own group, headed by James F. Gates Jr. '21, which was also studying the structure of the university and the functioning of the trustees in particular. This committee conferred with the student-faculty group several times, and in April 1969 the Trustees adopted a proposal worked out by the two structure committees and the Alumni Council for annually electing a senior to the Board of Trustees. Two months later, the Trustees set a ten-year term for charter trustees, replacing the retirement-at-70-rule which had allowed some individuals to serve as trustees for twenty years or more. The Trustee's nominating committee also consulted with the students and faculty on the Kelley Committee before recommending new board members-another major change. In May 1969, the Committee publicized their finals plans for a university-wide senate to be called the Council of the Princeton University Community (CPUC). Providing a forum through which all the major groups of the University could address problems and reach consensus, the first meeting of the Council took place on October 27, 1969. Typically the Council meets once a month, October through May, with special meetings as needed. Additionally, all Council meetings are open to the public. Much of the work of the Council is conducted through its standing committees, including the Executive Committee, Committees on Rights and Rules, Governance, Priorities, and Resources, and the Judicial Committee. Special committees also have been established from time to time. CPUC is primarily a deliberative and consultative body, with the authority to "consider and investigate" university policy, governance, and any general issue related to the welfare of the University. Recommendations are then made to the appropriate decision-making bodies, or to the appropriate officers, of the University.
College students -- United States -- Political activity.; Student participation in administration.; Universities and colleges -- United States -- Administration -- History.; Correspondence.; Memoranda.; Reports.; Institute for Defense Analyses.; Princeton university; Princeton University Council of the Princeton University Community.; Kelley, Stanley
- Series 1: Committee Administration, 1967-1971; 3 boxes; 2 items
  Conditions Governing Access
  Collection is open for research use.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1: Committee Administration, arranged in alphabetical order, is comprised of material that provides an overview of the activities of the administration of the Kelley Committee. As chair, Kelley maintained correspondence with administration, faculty, committee members, and various departments of the university. Included are the minutes of the Special Committee as well as interim and final reports. Also included are statements and guidelines for administrative and community services, courses of study, rules of conduct and the office of ombudsmen. A bibliography was compiled which includes subjects of the aims of higher education, financial problems and policies of universities, university personnel policies, and external relations, The organization and structure of boards of trustees, university administration, faculty rights and responsibilities, and student unrest and rebellion are also included in the bibliography. These folders retain Kelley's labeling. The materials in the remainder of the collection provide a detailed context to the topics in Kelley's files, and are divided into topical series and arranged alphabetically within each box to facilitate easier cross-referencing for the researcher.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Ad Hoc Committee on University Investments: South Africa, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Council: Proposals for Electing Young Alumni Trustees, 1969 March; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Trustees: Discussion, 1968 November-December; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Trustees: Discussion, 1969 January-October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bentley Report: Course Evaluation, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bernstein, M.: Memorandum on Conflict of Interest, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bibliography: Bibliographical Classification Forms, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bibliography: Complete, circa 1969; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bibliography: Suggestions and Drafts, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bibliographies: Covering Letter, 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Comments on Draft Report, 1969; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Comments on Draft Report, 1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Committee on Structure: Members, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Committee on Structure: Notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Committee on Structure: Origins, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Committee on Structure: Suggestions from University Community, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Administration, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Alumni, 1968; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Committee Members, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Departments, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Faculty, 1968; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: General, 1968; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Library, 1968; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1968-1970; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Other Universities, 1969; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: President, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Princeton University Press, 1969; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Princetonian, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Research Board, 1969; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Students, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Teller, "Constructive Uses for Nuclear Explosives" talk, 1970 November; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Town Relations, 1969; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Trustees, 1968; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: University Committees, 1967-1968; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Faculty Committee of Undergraduate Life: Proposals, 1969 January; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Faculty Meetings: Minutes, 1968 June-December; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Faculty Meetings: Minutes, 1969 January-December; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Faculty Meetings: Minutes, 1970 January-December; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Faculty Meetings: Minutes, 1971 January-December; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Faculty Resolutions: Approving Council, 1969 June; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Faculty Resolutions: Discipline Committee Procedures, 1969 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Report: Drafts, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Report: Drafts, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Report: A Proposal to Establish the Council of the Princeton University Committee, Manuscript for Press, 1969 May 15; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Report: A Proposal to Establish the Council of the Princeton University Committee, 1969 May; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Final Report: The Governing of Princeton University, 1970 April; 1 item
  - Final Resolutions and Press Releases of the Special Committee on the Structure of the University, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Human Relations Council: Proposal, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Interim Report: Draft, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Interim Report, 1968 November; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Meetings: Board of Trustees, Faculty, UGA (Summaries), 1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings, 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Graduate Students), 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Maruca, Mestres), 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Memorandum to Trustees), 1968 June 18-June 28; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Moran), 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Palmer), 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Pittendrigh), 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Rudenstein), 1968 Fall; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Sullivan), 1968 Fall; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Meetings: Committee Hearings (Trustees, Kipp and Coburn), 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Meetings of the Committee, 1968-1969 Fall; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Meetings of the Committee, 1968 Summer; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Meetings of the Committee, 1968 June 14-17; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Meetings of the Committee, 1968 June 18-28; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ombudsmen: Discussion and Background, 1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Princeton Reports (Kelley), 1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Princeton University Research Board: Charter, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Progress Report of the Committee of Fifteen, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Proposal to Establish the Council (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Requests for Information, 1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Research Board: Proposals on External Organizations, 1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Staff Council, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Administrative Services (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Committee on Resources (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Committee on the Future of the University (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Communication (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Community Council (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Course of Study (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Faculty (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Governing Boards (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Graduate Students (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Investment (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Ombudsman (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Relations with Local Community (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Research Board (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Statements and Guidelines: The Right to Reply (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Rules of Conduct, non-academic (Drafts, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Statements and Guidelines: Undergraduate Association (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Statements and Guidelines: University Store (Drafts), undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Students and the University: Advisory Committee on Policy, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - University Affairs (Kelley), 1968-1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Series 2: Committees, 1966-1972; 2 boxes
  Series 2: Committees contains correspondence, memoranda, and background materials on individual committees integrally allied with the Special Committee, and the initial discussions and first meetings of CPUC.
  Arranged alphabetically by committee.
  - Alumni Trustees: Discussion, 1969 January-October; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Discipline, 1966-1968; 1969; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Committee on External Relations, 1967-1969; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Governance, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Rights and Rules, 1970; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, 1968-1970; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Judicial Committee, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Presidential Search Committee, 1972; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Trustees: Biographies, undated; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Priorities Committee, 1970-1971; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Action on the Council of the Princeton University Community (CPUC), 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Council of the Princeton University Community (CPUC) Activities, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Council of the Princeton University Community (CPUC) Activities, 1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Discussions for a University Community Council, 1968 November-1969 January; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Drafts: Proposals for the Establishment of the Council of the Princeton University Community (CPUC), 1969; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Initial Draft: Proposal for the Establishment of the Council of the Princeton University Community (CPUC), 1969; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Student Organizations, 1967-1970; 1 box
  Series 3: Student Organizations holds discussions that recount the involvement of the Undergraduate Assembly (UGA) and Graduate Student Association (GSA).
  Arranged alphabetically by name of organization.
  - Graduate Student Ballot, 1968; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Graduate Student Organization: Departmental Surveys, 1969; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Student Organization (GSO): Draft Document, undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Princeton Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), 1968; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - A Report of the Undergraduate Assembly (UGA) Committee on Academics, 1970; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Undergraduate Assembly (UGA) Minutes, 1967-1968; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Undergraduate Assembly (UGA), 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Undergraduate Assembly (UGA) Minutes, 1969; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Undergraduate Education, 1968; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Undergraduate Student Departmental Committees, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The Union for National Draft Opposition (UNDO), 1970; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Universities Anti-War Fund: Candidates (UAWF), 1970; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Universities Anti-War Fund: Minutes (UAWF), 1970; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series 4: Institute for Defense Analysis, 1957-1970; 2 boxes
  Series 4: Institute for Defense Analysis contains the pivotal and often heated exchanges that took place between the university community and administration over the relationship of the University with IDA.
  - Faculty Opinions on the Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA), 1967 October-December; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Opinions on the Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA), 1968 January-September; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA): Annual Reports, 1957-1966; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA): Contract and Amendment, 1959; 1964; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA): Purpose and Nature, undated; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA) Reorganizes: Internal Reorganization Statement, 1967; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA): Report from the Board of Trustees, 1967; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Articles, 1967-1968; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Princeton Vietnam Assembly, 1968-1970; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Reaction to the Report of the Special Committee on IDA Trustees, undated; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Report & Faculty Resolutions with Regard to Security and Classification in Soviet Sponsored Research, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Reports of the Majority and the Minority of the Special Committee to Examine Princeton's Relationship to the Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA), 1968; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Special Committee on Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA) Relationship, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Statement: Graduate Students in the Department of Politics, 1967; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Statement: Princeton Young Republicans, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Statement: Students for a Democratic Society, 1967; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Statement: Undergraduate Assembly, 1968; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Strike Against U.S. Involvement in Indo-China, 1970; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "Student Political Opinion with Reference to the Trustees of Princeton University", 1968; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series 5: Faculty and Department Surveys, 1968; 2 boxes